<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by Ed Beach (Firaxis Games) -->
<GameData>
  <Language_en_US>


    <Row Tag="TXT_KEY_TRAIT_GREAT_ANDEAN_ROAD_SHORT">
      <Text>Great Andean Road</Text>
    </Row>
    <Row Tag="TXT_KEY_TRAIT_GREAT_ANDEAN_ROAD">
      <Text>Units ignore terrain costs when moving into any tile with Hills. No maintenance costs for improvements in Hills; half cost elsewhere.</Text>
    </Row>
    <Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_DAWN_INCA_TITLE">
      <Text>Inca</Text>
    </Row>
    <Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_DAWN_INCA_TEXT">
      <Text>Oh ye who remakes the world, your loyal subjects greet you - King Pachacuti! You rule the Inca people. From their beginnings in the small state of Cusco the Incans displayed their potential for greatness, marching to war against their many enemies, crushing their armies into dust and carving for themselves a mighty empire stretching from Ecuador to Chile. Indeed they built the greatest empire ever seen in pre-Columbian America. More than mere soldiers your people were great builders and artists as well, and the remnants of their works still awe and inspire the world today.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Oh King Pachacuti, truly are you called "Earth Shaker!" Will you once again call upon the ground itself to fight at your side?  Your armies await your signal. Will you restore the glory of your empire? Can you build a civilization that will stand the test of time?

      </Text>
    </Row>
    <Row Tag="TXT_KEY_TRAIT_SEVEN_CITIES_SHORT">
      <Text>Seven Cities of Gold</Text>
    </Row>
    <Row Tag="TXT_KEY_TRAIT_SEVEN_CITIES">
      <Text>[ICON_GOLD] Gold bonus for discovering a Natural Wonder (bonus enhanced if first to discover it). [ICON_CULTURE] Culture, [ICON_HAPPINESS_1] Happiness, and tile yields from Natural Wonders doubled.</Text>
    </Row>
    <Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_DAWN_SPAIN_TITLE">
      <Text>Spain</Text>
    </Row>
    <Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_DAWN_SPAIN_TEXT">
      <Text>Blessed Isabella, Servant of God, Holy Queen of Castile and León, your people greet and welcome you! You are the ruler of Spain, a beautiful and ancient country at the crossroads of the world between Europe and Africa, one shore on the Mediterranean and the other on the mighty Atlantic Ocean. The Spanish are a multicultural people, with roots in the Muslim and Christian world. A seafaring race, Spanish explorers found and conquered much of the New World, and for many centuries its gold and silver brought Spain unrivaled wealth and power, making the Spanish court the envy of the world.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]O fair and virtuous Isabella, will you rebuild the Spanish Empire and show the world again the greatness of your people?  Will you take up the mantle of the holy monarchy and vanquish your foes under Heaven's watchful eyes?  Your adoring subjects await your command. Can you build a civilization that will stand the test of time?

      </Text>
    </Row>
  </Language_en_US>
</GameData>
