<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<GameData>
	<!-- LocBuddy does not yet handle DLC scenarios so for now add the scenario text to the DLC package.-->
	<Language_en_US>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_TITLE">
			<Text>Rise of the Mongols</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_DESC">
			<Text>Ride with Genghis Khan and his Mongol horsemen to establish the largest continuous land empire ever seen.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_CIVSALIVE">
			<Text>Major Civs to Destroy: {1_CivsRemaining}[NEWLINE]Turns Left: {2_TurnsRemaining}</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_BRIEFING">
			<Text>Briefing</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_MARITIME_FALLEN">
			<Text>A maritime city-state has fallen to our Mongol forces. These common folk of this land have paid us a handsome ransom ({1_NumGold} gold) to preserve their lives.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_CULTURED_FALLEN">
			<Text>A cultured city-state has fallen to our Mongol forces. From these peoples we have unlocked the secrets of a new Social Policy. Choose a free Policy at your leisure, Great Khan.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_MAJOR_FALLEN">
			<Text>Congratulations, another major civilization has fallen to our Mongol riders. We have plundered huge riches ({1_NumGold} gold) from their treasury. We have also unlocked a new scientific discovery from studying their foreign ways. Choose a free Technology at your leisure, Great Leader.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_MAJOR_FALLEN_TO_ALLY">
			<Text>With some help from another power, another major civilization has fallen. We have plundered moderate riches ({1_NumGold} gold) from their treasury.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_ALMATY_FALLEN">
			<Text>The Almaty city-state has fallen to our Mongol forces. We have enlisted {1_NumUnits} of their Horsemen to our cause. You will find them near Karakorum, Great Khan.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_DALI_FALLEN">
			<Text>The Dali city-state has fallen to our Mongol forces. We have enlisted {1_NumUnits} of their Pikemen to our cause. You will find them near Karakorum, Great Khan.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_KOREA_FALLEN">
			<Text>The Korean city-state has fallen to our Mongol forces. We have enlisted {1_NumUnits} of their Crossbowmen to our cause. You will find them near Karakorum, Great Khan.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_XIA_FALLEN">
			<Text>The Western Xia city-state has fallen to our Mongol forces. We have enlisted {1_NumUnits} of their Horsemen to our cause. You will find them near Karakorum, Great Khan.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]You are advised to build a road connecting this city to your capital to collect trade income. You also may want to garrison the city with weak troops to keep the citizens here a bit happier.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_FREE_TECH">
			<Text>Free Tech from Conquering a Major Civ</Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_CIV5_DAWN_MONGOLIA_TEXT">
			<Text>
				SCENARIO DESCRIPTION[NEWLINE]All hail the mighty Khan, the new ruler of the united tribes of the Central Asian plateau! You have brought the Merkits, Naimans, Keraits, and Tatars under your domain, joining them with your own faithful Mongol Keshiks. Now that you command 5 tribes of horsemen, it is time to bring the rest of Eurasia under the Mongol yoke. But don't think this is necessarily an easy task - you must keep your greedy clansmen happy.  They have promised to stay faithful to your Yassa code only if you can provide them adequate spoils of war. So there is no time to waste: journey out across the steppes and let your conquests begin![NEWLINE][NEWLINE]VICTORY CONDITIONS[NEWLINE]Victory is yours if you can conquer 4 or more major civilizations before 100 turns have elapsed. (On Difficulty Levels higher than Prince, you will need to conquer more than 4.) Tarry longer than the allotted time and your compatriots will grow impatient, causing your once mighty empire to dissolve into squabbling fiefdoms.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]SPECIAL RULES[NEWLINE]The spoils you receive from conquest will be numerous and varied, all providing needed boosts and resources to continue pushing forward.  For example, the troops of militaristic city states will join your forces.  A cultural city state will provide a free social policy. And a maritime city state will provide extra gold for your treasury.  Best of all, for conquering a major civilization you will receive a free technology and even greater riches!
			</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_LEADER_RAMKHAMHAENG_FIRSTGREETING_1">
			<Text>Welcome, Stranger, to Northern China. I am Zhangzong. We are greatly honored by your visit.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_LEADER_RAMKHAMHAENG_FIRSTGREETING_2">
			<Text>I am honored to make your acquaintance. I am Zhangzong of the Jin Dynasty of Northern China.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_LEADER_RAMKHAMHAENG_FIRSTGREETING_3">
			<Text>Greetings. I am Zhangzong, Emperor of the Jin Dynasty. You do all of Northern China a great honor by visiting us.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_LEADER_ALEXANDER_FIRSTGREETING_1">
			<Text>I, Michael VIII, ruler of the restored Byzantine Empire, do greet you. May you prove to be a steadfast ally or worthy adversary!</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_LEADER_ALEXANDER_FIRSTGREETING_2">
			<Text>Greetings and well-met! I am Michael VIII Palaiologos, ruler of Byzantium. May you treat our lands more kindly than the knights of the Fourth Crusade!</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_LEADER_ALEXANDER_FIRSTGREETING_3">
			<Text>Welcome, stranger! I am Michael VIII, restorer of the Byzantine Empire. We greet you to our lands, recently reclaimed from the Latin knights of the Fourth Crusade!</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_CIV5_UIGHUR_TEXT">
			<Text>Founded in 742 AD, the Golden Age of the Uighur Empire quickly began and extended into the latter 8th century.  However, the young and fledgling empire was conquered by the Kyrgyz in 840, and the Uighur scattered into three kingdoms: Gansu, Turpan and Karakhanids. This scenario concerns the Uighur in Turpan, a fairly successful tribal kingdom which lasted until the Mongol invasion of 1389.  The Mongols eventually adopted Uighur script as their writing system after the Uighurs became their vassals.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_CIV5_GEORGIA_TEXT">
			<Text>Inhabited since the early Stone Age, the complete unification of the area did not occur until the 11th century AD, under King Bagrat V.  The new kingdom of Georgia quickly flourished and reached its zenith only one short century later.  This Georgian Renaissance brought a multitude of advancements to the area, including breakthroughs in philosophy, the penmanship of epic poetry, and the construction of exquisite cathedrals.  Despite its quick and successful development, the Georgian Golden Age came crashing to an end with the Mongol invasion in 1236; the kingdom completely collapsed by the end of the 15th century.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_CIV5_HUNGARY_TEXT">
			<Text>Founded in 895 AD, Hungary is one of the oldest countries in Europe.  For centuries the kingdom repelled many attacks against its borders and housed some of the wealthiest kings on the continent - at one point the Hungarian king's income doubled that of England's monarch.  In 1217, the crown led the Fifth Crusade into the Holy Land, in the process creating the largest royal army in the history of the Crusades.  However, not even this mighty army could stop the sweeping arm of the Mongolian Empire.  In 1241, the Mongols invaded Hungary and killed roughly half of the country's population, almost 1 million people.  The Hungarian king Béla IV ordered the construction of hundreds of stone fortifications along the borders, stopping some smaller forces, but the greatest damage had already been done.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_CIV5_DAI_VIET_TEXT">
			<Text>The Golden Age of the Dai Viet period of Vietnam started with the founding of the Ly dynasty in 1009 AD.  It is here when the country gained a formal strategic vision and started to focus more on building a strong economy and completing civil works projects. Seeing such a valuable jewel on its borders, the Mongols attempted to invade the Dai Viet in 1257, 1284, and 1288, all unsuccessfully.  The Dai Viet did what most other nations at the time could not - they avoided the superior Mongol forces in the open field and fought the horsemen only where they had the upper hand, securing the independence of their nation.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_CIV5_DALI_TEXT">
			<Text>Located in the modern Yunnan Province of China, the kingdom of Dali was founded in 937 AD after a period of turbulent, smaller dynasties.  The kingdom's territory lent itself naturally to defense, and it was said that just a few men could protect the valley for years.  This claim seems to hold some truth, as the Mongols attempted repeatedly to invade the kingdom, all unsuccessfully.  Records show that the Mongolian army eventually located a traitor from Dali to lead them over the mountains through a secret passage, finally giving them the means to overrun the impregnable defenses.  In 1253 the Mongols completed their invasion of the state, eventually creating the Province of Yunnan in 1274.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_CIV5_ABBASIDS_TEXT">
			<Text>The third of the Islamic caliphates, the Abbasid dynasty ruled the kingdom from the capital in Baghdad.  The caliphate was founded by descendents of the prophet Muhammad in 750 AD, and flourished for several hundred years.  The Abbasids continued to hold power for centuries, but their sway over the local provinces diminished over time.  In 1258 the Mongols invaded the caliphate and sacked Baghdad, removing the Abbasids from political power. The Caliphate was formally disestablished, with the Abbasids only managing to hold onto some small amount of religious authority.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_CIV5_CRUSADERS_TEXT">
			<Text>During the Western European crusades of the Holy Land, a number of small feudal states were created during the 12th and 13th centuries AD.  The first four Crusader states were created in the Levant, an area along the eastern shore of the Mediterranean.  Later during the Third Crusade, the Kingdom of Cyprus was founded by Richard the Lionhearted, where it continued to be a base for the Christian forces until 1571.  The Mongols never made any formal attacks against the Crusader states, and the majority survived until a round of invasions led by the Ottomans in the 16th century.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_CIV5_WESTERN_XIA_TEXT">
			<Text>The Western Xia Dynasty, or Tangut Empire, was founded in 1038 AD when a Tangut chieftain named himself emperor of the Da Xia region.  Not much later, the kingdom suffered massive destruction from rounds of Mongol invasions led by Genghis Khan - six different attacks over the course of twenty-two years. Genghis died during the last round of attacks (the cause of death still being debated), and the enraged horde overran the capital in 1227, destroying buildings and written records, murdering the emperor, and killing tens of thousands in the process.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_CIV5_KOREA_TEXT">
			<Text>At the time of the Mongolian Empire, the Kingdom of Korea was ruled by the Goryeo dynasty, which took power in 918 AD.  During this reign the nation flourished: its laws were codified, a civil service system was introduced,  and it made great cultural advancements with the creation of the world's first movable-metal-type printing press.  Starting in the 1230s however, the kingdom became threatened by Mongolian forces, who continued a heated invasion attempt for the next few decades.  In 1259 the nation sued for peace, and a treaty was drawn up between Korea and the Mongols.   The Goryeo were allowed to keep their sovereignty, while the Mongolian Empire annexed a large portion of the northern Provinces. </Text>
		</Row>

		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_CIV5_SIAM">
			<Text>Jin</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_CIV5_SIAM_HEADING_1">
			<Text>History</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_CIV5_SIAM_TEXT_1">
			<Text>
				The Jin Dynasty (also known as the Jurchen Dynasty) was established in 1115 AD in the area of northeast China historically known as Manchuria.  The Jurchens, a tribal people descended from the earlier Mohe tribes inhabiting this region, were primarily hunter-gatherers living as vassals under the Liao Dynasty. Unified under the guidance of Wanyan Aguda, leader of the Wanyan tribe, the Jurchens would quickly conquer the Liao and much of northern China. Wanyan would take the name "Jin" for his new Dynasty, meaning "Golden".[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Much like the Mongols, the Jurchen were known for their fearsome cavalry, whose talents are said to have developed as a result of the strong hunting traditions within the tribes. Having crushed the Liao with the assistance of the Song Dynasty, the Jurchens would invade Song territory, leading to nearly 20 years of continuous war. In 1141, the Treaty of Shaoxing would lead to peace between the two dynasties, creating a border at the Huai River.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]At its peak, the Jin Dynasty encompassed more than 30 million people and the entirety of Northern China. However, the rise of Genghis Khan brought new leadership to the neighboring Mongol tribes, and soon the Mongols would begin their legendary conquest of Asia, including the Jin.  By 1227, the year of Genghis Khan's death, the Mongols had decimated much of the Jin's forces. However, the valiant warriors of the Jin would manage to resist Mongol domination for another 7 years after Genghis' death, finally succumbing to the Mongol forces in 1234.
			</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_CIV5_GREECE">
			<Text>Byzantium</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_CIV5_GREECE_HEADING_1">
			<Text>History</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_CIV5_GREECE_TEXT_1">
			<Text>
				The ancient Greek city of Byzantium, destined to become the seat of power for two distinct empires, was founded in 667 BC by a Greek colonist named Byzas. Although the early history of Byzantium is intertwined with the legends of Greek mythology, historians are relatively confident that these settlers traveled from the Greek city of Megara after sailing across the Aegean Sea.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Strategically positioned near the trade routes connecting Europe to Asia, Byzantium quickly grew in size and prosperity. In 324 AD, the Roman Emperor Constantine would choose to rebuild Byzantium in the image of Rome itself, forming the new capital of the Eastern Roman Empire (known as the Byzantine Empire in the present day). The city would henceforth be known to the people as Constantinople, and would remain the capital of the Byzantine Empire until its fall some 1000 years later.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]In 1453 the Ottoman Empire would capture the city of Constantinople, sounding the death knell of the Byzantine Empire. The Ottoman ruler, Mehmed II, would however continue the legacy of Constantinople by declaring it the new capital of the Ottoman Empire.  Although known to the Turks as "Istanbul," the city would not be officially renamed until 1930.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]From Byzantium to Constantinople to Istanbul, the small Greek colony has grown from its early roots to become one of the world's largest and most prosperous cities. Modern Istanbul is considered a "megacity," with a population of over 13 million people, making it the largest city in Turkey.  A UNESCO World Heritage site, Istanbul continues the traditions of its past with a vast and varied array of social and cultural events occurring each year.
			</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_CIVILOPEDIA_LEADERS_RAMKHAMHAENG_NAME">
			<Text>Zhangzong</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_CIVILOPEDIA_LEADERS_RAMKHAMHAENG_SUBTITLE">
			<Text>Leader of the Jin Dynasty</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_CIVILOPEDIA_LEADERS_RAMKHAMHAENG_LIVED">
			<Text>1168 - 1208 AD</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_CIVILOPEDIA_LEADERS_ALEXANDER_NAME">
			<Text>Michael VIII</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_CIVILOPEDIA_LEADERS_ALEXANDER_SUBTITLE">
			<Text>Leader of the Byzantine Empire</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_MONGOL_SCENARIO_CIVILOPEDIA_LEADERS_ALEXANDER_LIVED">
			<Text>1224 - 1282 AD</Text>
		</Row>
	</Language_en_US>
</GameData>
