<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by Ed Beach (Firaxis Games) -->
<GameData>
	<Language_en_US>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_FEATURES_FOUNTAIN_YOUTH_TEXT">
			<Text>One of the earliest accounts of this legendary spring comes from Herodotus, who describes it as a special "Water of Life" giving any who drinks of it exceptionally long life.  Similar stories have also been told among the indigenous people of the Caribbean and South America, which brought the Fountain of Youth to prominence during Spain's era of exploration.  According to one popular story, in 1513 the Spanish conquistador Juan Ponce de Leon heard tales of the fountain during his travels in Puerto Rico, and set sail to search for eternal life.  In doing so, he discovered Florida (and become one of the first Europeans to set foot on American soil) but never did locate the mythical fountain.  The Fountain of Youth continues to captivate audiences today - movies, books, comics, and games have all featured the fabled spring and man's eternal quest to obtain it.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_FEATURES_FOUNTAIN_YOUTH_HELP">
			<Text>All units that are next to it heal at double rate for the rest of the game.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_FEATURES_POTOSI_TEXT">
			<Text>Located in southern Bolivia, the mountain of Potosi produced nearly all of the silver mined by the Spanish during their imperial days.  Once removed from the mountain, it was taken by llama and mule to the coast where it was then loaded onto treasure ships sailing back to Europe.   Nearly 41,000 tons of pure silver were mined over the course of 200 years, 8,200 of which went directly to the Spanish crown.  After 1800, the main silver mines were depleted, but the mining of Potosi still continues today - some for silver but now mostly for tin.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_FEATURES_EL_DORADO_TEXT">
			<Text>This fabled "Lost City of Gold" drew many Spanish conquistadors to the New World, all hoping to stumble upon its untold riches. For nearly three centuries, the myth of precious gems and gold drew explorers to the South American coasts, who often sacked other cities they found along the way. El Dorado has captivated explorers throughout the centuries, and expeditions as late as 1804 were arranged to divine its location. However, it is now believed that the mythical city was inspired by the name of a Muisca chief, who reportedly, as part of an initiation, covered himself in a fine layer of gold dust and dove into the Guatavita Lake.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_FEATURES_EL_DORADO_HELP">
			<Text>Grants 500 [ICON_GOLD] Gold to the first player to discover it.</Text>
		</Row>
	</Language_en_US>
</GameData>
