<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by Ed Beach (Firaxis Games) -->
<!--Sid Meier's Civilization V -->
<!--Copyright Firaxis Games 2010 -->
<GameData>
	<Language_en_US>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_1066_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_POWYS">
			<Text>Powys</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_1066_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_POWYS_ADJ">
			<Text>Powys</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_VIKING_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_POWYS_DESC">
			<Text>The Roman Empire marked out a territory in Britain between the Cambrian Mountains and Western Midlands, and built a capital at the site of modern Wroxeter called Viroconium Cornoviorum. As Roman power in Britain faded in the Dark Ages, a new state arose in the traditional lands of the Ordovices and Cornoviis, extending from the Cambrian Mountains to the Western Midlands. By the middle of the 5th Century AD, Powys was solidly established as a kingdom of Britain.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]The first and greatest ruling house of Powys was the Gwerthrynion, who claimed the legendary Vortigern as their founder. The historical warlord Vortigern would later become the model for the literary King Arthur, and the literary embellishment of Arthur has done something to mythologize the kingdom of Powys as well.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Early in the 6th Century, Powys was ravaged by the Northumbrians and portions annexed by their erstwhile allies the Mercians, but Powys stormed back, conquering territory from the English until by mutual agreement a border was established at Offa's Dyke in the middle of the 7th Century. Offa's Dyke remains today the border between Wales and England.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Powys was eventually subsumed by the Kingdom of Gwynedd on the death of the last Gwerthyrnion king in 855. When Howell the Good became king of Gwynedd in 942, he already ruled most of the lands that make up modern Wales. Through savvy politicking and legal reforms, he made his kingdoms into great powers on the island, codifying Welsh Law and creating the first indigenous Welsh coin since the Bronze Age. On Howell's death, Powys was given to one of his sons, but the greater Welsh kingdom was reassembled by his grandson Maredudd ab Owain.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Over time, the power of the great Welsh families waned, and invaders from Ireland and the Vikings chipped away at the throne of Powys, as usurpers seized the throne and were overthrown by pretenders of the old houses. By the time of the Norman Invasion, constant fractious warfare wracked the land, and William the Conquerer was content to leave Wales to his barons to deal with. They in turn made a complete hash of it.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_1066_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_GWYNEDD">
			<Text>Gwynedd</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_1066_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_GWYNEDD_ADJ">
			<Text>Gwynedd</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_VIKING_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_GWYNEDD_DESC">
			<Text>The Romans called the lands of the Ordovices, Gangani, and Deceangli "Venedotia," but the mountainous land on the Irish Sea was not a land under their control. As Roman power faded in Britain, the Kingdom of Gwynedd emerged, founded by the legendary Cunedda of Lothia. The land's name has been interpreted as meaning "Land of the War-Host," though the exact meaning is lost to time.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Gwynedd quickly became preeminent among the petty kingdoms of Wales. Maelgwyn the Tall in particular became the subject of many myths and legends, and was described by Gildas as one of the five greatest British Kings. Gildas also gave Maelgwyn a curious appellative - "Dragon of the Island" which may have morphed over time to "Pendragon" of literary fame. But Maelgwyn's death in 547 left a vacuum, and a series of succession wars followed. Gwynedd did ally with Powys to fight the Anglians in the early 6th century, and Cadwallon ap Cadfan launched a furious assault on the Northumbrians, sacking York in 633 and laying waste to the land.  He and his son Cadwaladr Fendigad became the last two High Kings of Britain.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]The house of Cunedda died off in the early 8th Century, and the house of Aberffraw (distantly related by ancestry) had to deal with incursions by the Vikings and Irish, ruling their subsidiary kingdom of Powys, and fighting with the other high Welsh families until they were overthrown by Howell the Good, who took the opportunity to straighten up the place and modernize it like those really progressive kingdoms in Wessex that had things like codified laws and their own money.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]By the Norman Invasion, Gwynedd had returned to fractious infighting amongst its nobles, and William the Conquer let his barons subjugate Wales as they could. But Norman authority held only tenuously in Gwynedd's high mountain lands and in the hearts of its people, who still remembered when they had been kings.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_1066_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_NORTHUMBRIA">
			<Text>Northumbria</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_1066_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_NORTHUMBRIA_ADJ">
			<Text>Northumbrian</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_VIKING_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_NORTHUMBRIA_DESC">
			<Text>The adjoining kingdoms of Deira and Bernecia were united by force when King Aethelfrith of Bernicia conquered Deira in 604. But this victory was short-lived, and when Aethelfrith was killed in 616, the son of the former king of Deira, Edwin, was made king of the combined lands. But it was not until the rule of King Oswald in 634 that Northumbria was finally consolidated into a single Anglian kingdom. Oswald quickly expanded his kingdom and Christianized it with the help of Saint Aidan of Iona.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Northumbria was often at war with Mercia. Oswald was killed in battle with the Mercians in 650, and the Picts rose up and defeated the Northumbrians in 685. A brief period of stability under the reign of Aldfrith followed, but Northumbria had lost its prestige and power, and was conquered by the Danish brothers Halfdan Ragnarsson and the colorfully-named Ivar the Boneless.  A brief uprising by Aella of Northumberland was brutally suppressed. Now subject to the Danelaw, a series of puppet kings ruled Northumberland until Erik Bloodaxe in 954. From then on, Northumberland was no kingdom, but a mere Earldom.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]William the Conquerer quickly set his eyes on Northumbria, recognizing it as a valuable buffer against the North, and as a symbol to resistance to his rule. He attempted to install one of his barons as an overlord, but the baron and 700 of his retainers were slaughtered in the city of Durham. This led William to conduct a punitive campaign into Northumbria, partitioning it into an Earldom seated in Durham, and the region of Northumberland. The Normans built the city of Newcastle to secure their hold on this new territory of theirs, but the hold was tentative. The lands of Northumbria were long afterwards a fractious border country, rebelling against rule from the south and fighting the protracted border war with the Scots to the North.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_1066_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_GALLOWAY">
			<Text>Galloway</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_1066_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_GALLOWAY_ADJ">
			<Text>Galloway</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_VIKING_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_GALLOWAY_DESC">
			<Text>At the tip of Southwestern Scotland is the Gall-Ghaidhealaibh - the land of the foreign Gaels. Isolated by its rugged coastline and hilly northern border, it was nonetheless drawn on Ptolemy's map of Britain. The Romans called the inhabitants the Novantae, and the missionary Saint Ninian built a church here, but much of its history is shrouded in legend. The Welsh poets believed that one of King Arthur's Three Thrones of Britain was in Galloway, called Pen Rhionydd.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]At some point in the late 7th century, Galloway was wrestled from control of the Britons by the Kingdom of Bernicia, who displaced the locals from the flat arable land and forced them into the hills. But the remoteness of the region meant it was easy prey for the Vikings and the Irish (especially the Irish Vikings) for whom the territory was just a short hop across the Irish Sea.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]The Norse Gaels, the Gall-Gaedhil, are the best-known inhabitants of Galloway. The Norse controlled the Irish Sea, and their settlements dotted its edges. Despite their Gaelic that they shared with the nascent Scots, they were indisputably their own people, sailing from their isolated lands to wreak havoc on the coastlines of Britain. This isolation meant that the Lords of Galloway were effectively kings on their own until late in the Middle Ages, starting with Suibne mac Cináeda in the early 10th century and extending until the 12th. Though nominally under the High King of Scotland, they could ignore or pay tribute to him as their power allowed.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]The Law of Galloway lasted another two centuries after their Lords lost power, a tribute to the splendid isolation of the land and people of Galloway.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_1066_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_SCOTLAND">
			<Text>Scotland</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_1066_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_SCOTLAND_ADJ">
			<Text>Scottish</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_VIKING_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_SCOTLAND_DESC">
			<Text>There have been people living in the north of Britain since the end of the last ice age, about 8,500 years before the Romans recorded works on the island. Neolithic ruins in Scotland predate the famous Skara Brae of the Orkneys, and archeological evidence reveals evidence of warring communities living in fortified villages through the Iron Age.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]The Caledonians fought hard and often successfully against the Romans in Britain, forcing them to retreat from their tentative forts and outposts behind Hadrian's Wall. The land was occupied by the Picts and Britons thereafter, until the Dark Ages, when the Irish, Anglo-Saxons, and then Vikings invaded and created permanent settlements in Scotland. Saint Ninian's mission brought Christianity to the region around 450 AD, although apparently the Picts then renounced it until Saint Columba arrived in 563.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Legend has it that the Picts were betrayed by the Scots king Kenneth Mac Alpin, who invited the Pictish king Drest and his nobles to a feast, plied them with drink, and then pulled the pins from their benches, sending them into spikey pits concealed beneath.  The truth is somewhat less fanciful - Mac Alpin had claim to the crown of both kingdoms, and managed to combine them into what would become the Kingdom of Alba.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]The Kingdom of Alba became the core of what is recognized as Scotland. Through conquest and expansion, the kingdom of Strathclyde was added, and the southern barrier pushed to the River Tweed - the modern-day Southeastern border of Scotland.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]King Duncan led an expedition to try to seize the lands of his rival Macbeth around 1039. The expedition was a terminal disaster for Duncan, who was killed in battle, and Macbeth then became the king of the Scots. It should be noted that the conflict between Macbeth and Duncan was the basis for Shakespeare's play, and is historically accurate if you ignore such simple details as the age of both Duncan and Macbeth, the stated relationship between the two men, and the entire chronology given in  the play. Duncan's son Malcolm did follow Macbeth as king of Scotland, so at least he got that part right. And as King James was Shakespeare's patron, a colorful reinterpretation of history that flattered the man paying the bills is perhaps understandable.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]When William the Conquerer invaded Britain, Edgar the Aethling sought refuge in Scotland with an eye to claiming his kingship to the south, but by 1072 William had successfully invaded Scotland and forced Malcolm (who had become king in 1057) to pay him tribute and hostages.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_1066_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_MUNSTER">
			<Text>Munster</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_1066_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_MUNSTER_ADJ">
			<Text>Munster</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_VIKING_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_MUNSTER_DESC">
			<Text>Munster, in the southwest of Ireland, is one of the five great kingdoms of Ireland. In the second century, Ptolemy records the land as belonging to the Iverni tribe. According to legend, Bodb Derg was the second King of the Tuatha De Danann and the first of the Kings of Munster. The Eoganachta dynasty ruled from  the 7th century,  after the conquests of Failbe Flann mac Aedo Duib. The Eoganachta would in time become one of Ireland's most important clans, though they never became High Kings.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]The Vikings invaded starting in the 8th Century, and would in time found the cities of Cork, Waterford, and Limerick.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]The last great High King of Ireland, Brian Boru, first proclaimed himself King of Munster before he was able to wrestle control of the kingship from the Ui Neill. His descendants, the O'Brians, were hereditary rulers of Munster as well, until the dissolution of the kingdom in the early 12th Century.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]By 1118, Munster had fractured into three smaller kingdoms: Thomond, Desmond, and Omond.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_1066_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_MEATH">
			<Text>Meath</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_1066_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_MEATH_ADJ">
			<Text>Meathian</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_VIKING_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_MEATH_DESC">
			<Text>For 1000 years, Mide, or Meath, was the central Kingdom of Ireland, both geographically and spiritually. Tradition dates the founding of Meath to the First Century AD, by Tuathal Techtmar, ancestor of the great Niall of the Nine Hostages.  Tuathal carved himself a kingdom from territory seized from Ulster, Leinster, Connacht, and Munster and named the resulting territory Meath. The Ui Neill kings of the South were the traditional rulers of Meath.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Meath's importance to the High Kings of Ireland was further enhanced because the Hill of Tara was situated there. The Hill of Tara is a complex of barrows and earthworks dating back to the Iron Age, and traditionally the place where the High King was crowned. The Hill of Tara has been used as a ritual location since the Neolithic, and was the spiritual heart of Ireland until the 12th Century, though its importance declined with the ascension of the British and the expansion of Christianity.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Whether or not the Irish High Kings sat in court on the Hill of Tara or not, Meath's central location in Ireland and its proximity to the Norse Irish settlements made it a kingdom of great importance. The Battle of Clontarf was fought on its soil, where the last great High King of Ireland, Brian Boru, fell.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_1066_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_CONNACHT">
			<Text>Connacht</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_1066_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_CONNACHT_ADJ">
			<Text>Connacht</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_VIKING_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_CONNACHT_DESC">
			<Text>Great tomb complexes in the northwest of Ireland speak to the presence of people there since the glaciers retreated at the end of the last ice age. Irish legends tell that when the Tuatha De Dannan invaded the land and fought the Fir Bolg, they were so impressed by the Fir Bolg that they gave them a quarter of the island - the area that would become the kingdom of Connacht.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Unambiguous reference to the area begins around the 6th Century AD in the Annals of Ulster, marking the death of prominent lords of that realm. The Vikings arrived at Connacht at the start of the 9th Century, and around this time the ruling house of Connacht was founded by Conchobar mac Taidg Mor, and the O Conchobair ruled Connacht until the middle of the 15th Century. The rulers of Connacht were often at war with the other Irish kingdoms, as well as the British and the Vikings who were settling Ireland.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]In Connacht, there are two mysterious megaliths - the Turoe Stone and the Castlestrange Stone, which are covered in carvings of a style and date commonly associated with mainland Europe during the Iron Age. The stones were likely brought to Ireland and moved over time, away from the successive waves of invaders who came to the land.</Text>
		</Row>
	</Language_en_US>
</GameData>
