<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by Ed Beach (Firaxis Games) -->
<!--Sid Meier's Civilization V -->
<!--Copyright Firaxis Games 2010 -->
<GameData>
	<Language_en_US>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_TROY">
			<Text>Troy</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_TROY_ADJ">
			<Text>Trojan</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_TROY_DESC">
			<Text>The legendary city of Troy, presumed to have reached its pinnacle in the 3rd and 2nd millennium BC, was a prosperous center of trade on the Aegean Sea. Featured predominantly in Homer's epic poem the "Iliad," the city was long thought to have been purely mythological. However, archaeological discoveries in the 19th century unearthed remnants in modern Turkey believed to have been the city of Troy.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_KNOSSOS">
			<Text>Knossos</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_KNOSSOS_ADJ">
			<Text>Knossian</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_KNOSSOS_DESC">
			<Text>The settlement of Knossos, found on the Greek island of Crete, was home to the ancient Bronze Age civilization of the Minoans. Influencing Greek society throughout the second millennium BC, the Minoans of Knossos are said to have been skilled craftsmen who often traded with the Egyptians.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_BYBLOS">
			<Text>Byblos</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_BYBLOS_ADJ">
			<Text>Byblosian</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_BYBLOS_DESC">
			<Text>One of the oldest cities in the world, the Phoenician settlement of Byblos, located in modern Lebanon, was founded sometime in the 5th millennium BC. Originally known as Gebal, the name "Byblos" (from the Greek "Bublos," for Papyrus) was given by the Greeks because the city served as the primary importer of Egyptian papyrus.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_UGARIT">
			<Text>Ugarit</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_UGARIT_ADJ">
			<Text>Ugaritic</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_UGARIT_DESC">
			<Text>The ancient city of Ugarit, located on the eastern Mediterranean Sea, is found today in modern Syria. Settled sometime in the 6th millennium BC, Ugarit developed as a successful port city, trading with the Egyptians and Greeks during its height in the late 2nd millennium.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_KYRENE">
			<Text>Cyrene</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_KYRENE_ADJ">
			<Text>Cyrenaic</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_KYRENE_DESC">
			<Text>The ancient Greek colony of Cyrene, found in modern-day Libya, was first settled in 630 BC by Greek colonists from the island of Thera. Becoming a center of commerce in the region, Cyrene was the hub of various trade routes connecting the other Greek colonies in the region.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_STOBI">
			<Text>Stobi</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_STOBI_ADJ">
			<Text>Stobi</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_STOBI_DESC">
			<Text>The ancient town of Stobi was at one time the Roman capital of the province of "Macedonia Salutaris," in present-day Macedonia. A strategically placed center of trade on the Crna and Axios rivers, Stobi was destroyed by an earthquake in 518 AD.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_SEUTHOPOLIS">
			<Text>Seuthopolis</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_SEUTHOPOLIS_ADJ">
			<Text>Seuthopolitan</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_SEUTHOPOLIS_DESC">
			<Text>Founded in the 4th century BC by the Thracian king Seuthes III, the city of Seuthopolis served as the capital of the Odrysian kingdom before being sacked by the Celts in 281 BC. The ruins of Seuthopolis are found in present-day Bulgaria.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_ENKOMI">
			<Text>Enkomi</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_ENKOMI_ADJ">
			<Text>Enkomi</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_ENKOMI_DESC">
			<Text>The city of Enkomi served as an important center of the copper trade during the 2nd millennium BC. Situated on the island of Cyprus, Enkomi prospered until c. 1050 BC when it was severely damaged by an earthquake and abandoned.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_ELAM">
			<Text>Elam</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_ELAM_ADJ">
			<Text>Elamite</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_ELAM_DESC">
			<Text>Elam, found in present-day Iran, was a wide-ranging territory that encompassed several provinces of Iran as well as portions of Iraq. Existing for several thousand years beginning in the 3rd millennium BC, Elam succumbed to internal strife as well as external conflicts near the dawn of the 1st century AD. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_NAKHCHIVAN">
			<Text>Nakhchivan</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_NAKHCHIVAN_ADJ">
			<Text>Nakhchivan</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_NAKHCHIVAN_DESC">
			<Text>Spanning territories in Armenia, Iran and Turkey, the landlocked region of Nakhchivan is said to have been colonized more than 5,000 years ago. Throughout its history the region would be embroiled in a number of military campaigns involving the Persian empires as well as the Macedonians. Nakhchivan still exists today as a region of the Republic of Azerbaijan. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_WASHUKANNI">
			<Text>Washukanni</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_WASHUKANNI_ADJ">
			<Text>Washukanni</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_WASHUKANNI_DESC">
			<Text>The city of Washukanni served as the capital of the Hurrian kingdom of the Mitanni people during the 2nd millennium BC. Although its exact location is still unknown today, it is thought to have existed along the banks of the Khabur River. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_SHARUHEN">
			<Text>Sharuhen</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_SHARUHEN_ADJ">
			<Text>Sharuhen</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_SCENARIO_CITYSTATE_SHARUHEN_DESC">
			<Text>The ancient town of Sharuhen, found in the Negev Desert of southern Israel, was at one time a refuge for the Hyksos people who were expelled from Egypt in the 16th century BC. The settlement was later destroyed by the Egyptian Pharaoh Ahmose I.</Text>
		</Row>
	</Language_en_US>
</GameData>
