<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by Scott Lewis (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization V -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2010 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text Objects -->
<GameData>
	<Language_en_US>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_BUILDING_STATUE_ZEUS">
			<Text>Statue of Zeus</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TEMPLE_ARTEMIS">
			<Text>Temple of Artemis</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MAUSOLEUM_HALICARNASSUS">
			<Text>Mausoleum of Halicarnassus</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_STATUE_ZEUS_HELP">
			<Text>+1 [ICON_CULTURE] Culture. All units gain +15% [ICON_STRENGTH] combat strength when attacking cities.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_TEMPLE_ARTEMIS_HELP">
			<Text>+10% [ICON_FOOD] Growth in all cities. +15% [ICON_PRODUCTION] Production when building ranged units.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_MAUSOLEUM_HALICARNASSUS_HELP">
			<Text>Gain 200 [ICON_GOLD] Gold each time a Great Person is expended. Each source of [ICON_RES_MARBLE] Marble or [ICON_RES_STONE] Stone worked by this City produces +2 [ICON_GOLD] Gold.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_STATUE_ZEUS_DESC">
			<Text>Standing over 40 feet tall (12m), the Statue of Zeus found in the Temple of Zeus at Olympia, Greece was another of the Seven Wonders of the Ancient World. Known to have been constructed by the Greek sculptor Phidias c. 440 BC, even with Zeus seated on a golden throne, the enormous statue could barely be contained by the temple itself. The statue is thought to have been destroyed no later than 425 AD, when the temple of Zeus was burned.  Whether the statue was still present at that time is the subject of much debate.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_TEMPLE_ARTEMIS_DESC">
			<Text>The Temple of Artemis, a Greek temple first constructed in 880 BC, was dedicated to the Goddess Artemis who represented the wilderness, the hunt and the moon. Originally built in the city of Ephesus, the temple is said to have been destroyed and rebuilt no less than seven times, the victim of both natural and man-made disasters. Considered one of the Seven Wonders of the Ancient World, the site was rediscovered by British archaeologists in the late 1800s, and today is marked by a single column made up of excavated remnants found at the site.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_MAUSOLEUM_HALICARNASSUS_DESC">
			<Text>The Mausoleum of Halicarnassus was constructed c. 350 BC as a tomb for Mausolus, the ruler of Caria (an area of modern Turkey). Said to have been designed and constructed by the greatest sculptors and craftsmen of the time, the temple was known for its detailed sculptural reliefs and impressive scale, towering nearly 150 feet high (47m). Destroyed by a series of earthquakes that struck the region during the 1st millennium AD, portions of the tomb were excavated by British archaeologists in the mid 19th century. One of the Seven Wonders of the Ancient World, the term "Mausoleum" as it is used today traces its origins to this tomb. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_STATUE_ZEUS_QUOTE">
			<Text>[NEWLINE][TAB][TAB]"He spoke, the son of Kronos, and nodded his head with the dark brows, and the immortally anointed hair of the great god swept from his divine head, and all Olympos was shaken."[NEWLINE][TAB][TAB] - The Iliad[NEWLINE][TAB]</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_TEMPLE_ARTEMIS_QUOTE">
			<Text>[NEWLINE][TAB][TAB]"It is not so much for its beauty that the forest makes a claim upon men's hearts, as for that subtle something, that quality of air, that emanation from old trees, that so wonderfully changes and renews a weary spirit."[NEWLINE][TAB][TAB] - Robert Louis Stevenson[NEWLINE][TAB]</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_WONDER_MAUSOLEUM_HALICARNASSUS_QUOTE">
			<Text>[NEWLINE][TAB][TAB]"The whole earth is the tomb of heroic men and their story is not given only on stone over their clay but abides everywhere without visible symbol woven into the stuff of other men's lives."[NEWLINE][TAB][TAB] - Pericles[NEWLINE][TAB]</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_PROMOTION_STATUE_ZEUS">
			<Text>Statue of Zeus</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_PROMOTION_STATUE_ZEUS_HELP">
			<Text>+15% [ICON_STRENGTH] Combat Strength when attacking cities.</Text>
		</Row>
	</Language_en_US>
</GameData>
